Implicit Association Tests: Stimuli Validation from Participant Responses

Project details

EC number 2021-FGW PSYL-13105

ID 13105

Title Implicit Association Tests: Stimuli Validation from Participant Responses

Department Psycho linguistics

Status Approved

Created 2021-02-10 09:13:47 **Modified** 2021-03-16 16:05:47

Project collaborators

Sally Hogenboom Owner s.a.m.hogenboom@uva.nl

Roland Pfau Ethics Member | R.Pfau@uva.nl | 0205253022

General

Responsible researcher

PhD Student: S.A.M. Hogenboom Supervisor: K. Schulz (ILLC) Supervisor: L. van Maanen (Utrecht University)

Who conducts the research?

We wish to use an existing data set. As of such the research was already conducted by the Project Implicit team from Harvard University (https://www.projectimplicit.net/about-us/). The data is collected on a publicly available demonstration website (https://implicit.harvard.edu/implicit/takeatest.html). The analyses of the data will be coded by the PhD student S.A.M. Hogenboom. Both the PhD student and the supervisors will interpret the outcomes of the analyses.

Research location

The data was collected via an online demonstration website:

https://implicit.harvard.edu/implicit/takeatest.html. This website has been publicly available since 1998.

Brief project description

The Implicit Association Test (IAT) is very popular in psychological research. When researchers create new IATs, they have to choose the categories and exemplars (i.e. stimuli) they deem suitable. Although some guidelines exist for choosing the stimuli, quantifiable criteria to validate the stimuli post-hoc are currently lacking. We want to use existing data of 15 IATs - partially available via the Project Implicit OSF (https://osf.io/y9hiq/wiki/home/) - to explore the validity of the included exemplars. We conduct mout of n bootstraps to determine the reliability of inferring exemplar validity from experimental response data. This analyses builds on the suggestion of Greenwald et al. (2019) who proposed that validity may be inferred from average response times and error percentages. We then use the bootstrapped parameters to explore whether exemplars that are re-used across IATs have similar validity estimates. Finally, we explore whether exemplar type (nouns, names, images) has an effect on the validity of exemplars.

Expected duration of the project

The data already exists, but there are a few aspects that will influence the duration of the project: 1. We want to preregister a report at "The British Journal of Social Psychology". The full duration of the project will thus be influenced by the speed at which the Stage 1 manuscript is reviewed, and hopefully approved. 2. In order to run our analyses we need to request additional data from the Project Implicit team. This has been very rapid for our pilot analyses. However, they estimate it may take up to 6 weeks for us to receive the data. 3. We have to code and run all our analyses. Especially the data preparations and cleaning may take a long time to run. We then, of course, also have to write the Stage 2 manuscript (results and discussion). All in all we expect the full project to take at least 6 months.

Expected number of participants

0

This project is comparable with the following EC-project (number)

N/A

GDPR Checklist

Will you be working with human participants?

No

We will be working with an existing data set from the Project Implicit demonstration website. We were advised by G. Lindeboom to thus answer this question with "No".

Will you collect personal data?

Yes

We will be working with existing datasets. The publicly available data of Project Implicit (https://osf.io/y9hiq/) contains personal information on gender, age, occupation etc. The raw data - which we will request from the team - does not contain personal information.

What personal data relating to subjects are recorded?

- Age / Date of birth
- Gender
- Education
- Race or Ethnic background
- Sexual orientation
- Political preferences
- Other, please explain in a comment below

Project Implicit has provided full 'codebooks' (https://osf.io/y9hiq/) which include detailed information on the included questions and how the answers were coded. The personal data that is recorded per participant differs depending on the Implicit Association Test they completed. It may thus me the case that some participants provided their sexual orientation in the "Sexuality IAT", whereas participants whom responded to a different IAT would not have provided this information. In our analyses we use the following demographic information to exclude participants: Age, Country of Citizenship, and Country of Residence. Even though information on, for example, race is available, we do not utilize the data in our analyses.

Responsible party

• Myself, as a researcher employed by the UvA together with an external non-commercial party in the EU (e.g., researchers from another EU-university (please supply contact information in a comment below))

The data was collected by Project Implicit (https://implicit.harvard.edu/implicit/contact.html). The demonstration website is non-commercial, and the cleaned and processed data is freely available via https://osf.io/y9hiq/. Project Implicit is also a non-profit company that provides support to researchers and companies who wish to conduct Implicit Association Tests (https://www.projectimplicit.net/). The data are curated by the Project Implicit team. The data analyses and interpretations are supervised by Leendert van Maanen, who is currently employed by Utrecht University (https://www.uu.nl/staff/LvanMaanen?t=0).

Who will be processing the data?

• Myself, as a researcher employed by the UvA together with an external non-commercial party outside the EU (e.g., researchers from a non EU-university (please supply contact information in a comment below))

The data was collected by Project Implicit (https://implicit.harvard.edu/implicit/contact.html). The demonstration website is non-commercial, and the cleaned and processed data is freely available via https://osf.io/y9hiq/. Project Implicit is also a non-profit company that provides support to researchers and companies who wish to conduct Implicit Association Tests (https://www.projectimplicit.net/). The data are curated - but not analyses - by the Project Implicit team. The data analyses and interpretations are supervised by Leendert van Maanen, who is currently employed by Utrecht University (https://www.uu.nl/staff/LvanMaanen?t=0).

Personal data is shared with which external (to the UvA) parties?

Other, please explain in a comment below

The data is retrieved from an external party, namely Project Implicit (https://osf.io/y9hiq/; https://implicit.harvard.edu/implicit/contact.html; https://www.projectimplicit.net/). The data is also processed under the supervision of Leendert van Maanen, currently employed by Utrecht University (https://www.uu.nl/staff/LvanMaanen?t=0)

On what GDPR basis will the data be processed?

On the basis of 'informed consent' e.g. the subject has actively agreed that his personal data will be processed during the research project

Text from the Project Implicit website: Preliminary Information On the next page

you'll be asked to select an Implicit Association Test (IAT) from a list of possible topics. We will also ask you (optionally) to report your attitudes or beliefs about these topics and provide some information about yourself. We ask these questions because the IAT can be more valuable if you also describe your own selfunderstanding of the attitude or stereotype that the IAT measures. We would also like to compare differences between people and groups. Data Privacy: Data exchanged with this site are protected by SSL encryption. Project Implicit uses the same secure hypertext transfer protocol (HTTPS) that banks use to securely transfer credit card information. This provides strong security for data transfer to and from our website. IP addresses are routinely recorded, but are completely confidential. We make the anonymous data collected on the Project Implicit Demonstration website publicly available. You can find more information on our Data Privacy page. Important disclaimer: In reporting to you results of any IAT test that you take, we will mention possible interpretations that have a basis in research done (at the University of Washington, University of Virginia, Harvard University, and Yale University) with these tests. However, these Universities, as well as the individual researchers who have contributed to this site, make no claim for the validity of these suggested interpretations. If you are unprepared to encounter interpretations that you might find objectionable, please do not proceed further. You may prefer to examine general information about the IAT before deciding whether or not to proceed. You can contact our research team (implicit@fas.harvard.edu) or Harvard's Committee on the Use of Human Subjects (cuhs@harvard.edu) for answers to pertinent questions about the research and your rights, as well as in the event of a research-related injury to yourself. I am aware of the possibility of encountering interpretations of my IAT test performance with which I may not agree. Knowing this, I wish to proceed

How long will the data be stored?

The data is owned by an external party. As of such we have no control over how long the data will be stored/publicly available. We do, however, have permission to store the subsets of data and the analyses scripts on our projects' github (https://github.com/bias-barometer).

Where are the data to be stored?

- Surfdrive
- Other, please explain in a comment below

We currently have all datasets processed and saved on Surfdrive. This also includes our analyses scripts. In order to support open science we will make the data (which was anonymised by Project Implicit) and our analyses freely available via Github (https://github.com/bias-barometer) and the Open Science Framework.

What security measures have been taken?

• Anonymisation (identifying data has been irreversibly destroyed)

Project history

2021-03-19 15:16:03 Project approved [by Roland Pfau]

Good luck with the project and best regards, Roland.

© 2021-03-16 16:15:13 Project submitted for review. [by Sally Hogenboom]

We have had to slightly revise the project for the previous ethics submission. Specifically, we have revised our research plan to include less and different analyses. We have also added one IAT and have now formally had approval from Project Implicit that we may store the data on Github/OSF.

- **© 2021-03-16 16:04:37** Project approval reverted. [by Sally Hogenboom]
- 2021-02-17 12:47:24 Project approved [by Roland Pfau]

Good luck with the research.

Best regards,

Roland Pfau

- 2021-02-17 12:43:15 Ethics member Roland Pfau (rpfau1) has been added. [by Roland Pfau]
- **© 2021-02-12 10:03:34** Project submitted for review. [by Sally Hogenboom]
- **© 2021-02-10 09:13:47** Project created [by Sally Hogenboom]